Pavel V. Fomin

Information Technology Consultant

Location: Plymouth, MN, USA
LinkedIn: http://www.linkedin.com/in/pfomin
Email: pavel.fomin@yahoo.com

Profile

- Over 20 years of software design and development experience in diverse industry environment
- Strong expertise in Java and JEE architecture with various Application and Web servers
- Solid RDBMS and NoSQL background

Skills Summary

Operating Systems Linux (Mint, Ubuntu, Redhat, SUSE), Unix (Solaris, AIX, SCO), Mac OS X, MS Windows

Languages Java 1.1-1.8, XML, WSDL, SQL, UML, Groovy, Bash, HTML, JavaScript, CSS Frameworks JSE/JEE: JAX-RS, JAX-WS, JDBC, JMS, JMX, EJB, JSP, JSTL, JSF, Servlets

Spring: Spring Core 2/3/4, MVC, JDBC Template, Security, Web Services, Rest Template,

AMQP, Spring Data, Spring Data Solr

Databases NoSQL: Riak, MongoDB

Relational: Oracle 7/8/9/10g/11g, MySQL, MS SQL Server, Sybase

Application Servers Tomcat 3/4/5/6/7, Liferay Portal Server 6.2, IBM Websphere Application Server 4/5/6/7, IBM

Websphere Portal Server 6.1, OAS 10g, Resin, BEA Weblogic 4.5.1/5.1/6.1, Borland Inprise

Application Server 4.x, JBoss, Apache Web Server, Oracle Web Server 2.1.1

Tools IDE: Eclipse, Intellij, Emacs

Methodologies Agile, SCRUM, Test Driven Development

Industries Retail, Medical supplies, Education, Finance, Banking, E-commerce, Healthcare, Medical

Software, Software Development, Energy Management, Telematics

Work History

<u>Solution Design Group</u>, Professional Services Senior Consultant

10/2014 - Present

McKesson Medical-Surgical, Web Development

Environment: Tomcat 7.x, Oracle 11g, Azure and private VMware cloud platforms, Linux, Windows 7 **Tools:** JDK 1.8, Spring Boot 1.5, Spring 4.x, Maven, Gradle, Eclipse (Mars), Emacs, Git, Bamboo, Oracle VirtualBox, Jira, DynaTrace

Created two new spring-boot based micro services to provide patient and formulary functionality, enable independent scalabitlity and cloud deployment. Helped establish best practices in test driven development, automated build and deployment processes. Ran several Docker POCs using Docker Swarm, Kubernetes, and Cloud Foundry using Azure and private VMware cloud platforms. Assisted project managers with running agile projects using SCRUM methodology and taking full advantage of Jira.

Best Buy, Cloud Services Development

Environment: Tomcat 7.x, Riak, Memcached, Ehcache, Amazon EC2, OpenStack, Akamai, Linux, Mac OS X Tools: JDK 1.7 / 1.8, Spring 4.x, Groovy, Spock, Intellij, Emacs, Git, Maven, Gradle, Jenkins, Oracle VirtualBox, Jira

Created highly scalable aggregation and transformation services for BestBuy.com to support functionality of new business initiatives. Implemented various architectural initiatives including domain services development, service integration with Node rendering tier and responsive front end redesign using Groovy and Spring framework in Amazon EC2 and OpenStack cloud environments. Used Akamai CDN and Edge Side Includes to offload edge traffic while providing configurable cache expiration and flushing capabilities of page fragments. Utilized Memcached and Ehcache to increase performance of the services tier.

McKesson Medical-Surgical, Web Development

Environment: Liferay 6.2 EE, Tomcat 7.x, Oracle 11g, Windows 7, Linux

Tools: JDK 1.7, Spring 4.0, Solr, Nutch, JSP, Freemarker, jQuery, Sass, Bourbon with Bitters and Neat, Maven, Eclipse (Luna), Emacs, CVS, Git, Jenkins, Jira, DynaTrace

Implemented new public web site for McKesson using Liferay 6.2 EE Portal server enabling content authors to publish changes without application code deployment. Created several Liferay portal plugins to customize the Liferay implementation for the client. Setup clustered site search using separate Solr server and Liferay Solr plugin. Used DynaTrace to identify the performance bottlenecks during the load tests.

Data Recognition Corporation, Information Services

Senior Software Developer

10/2013 - 10/2014

Environment: JEE, Tomcat 7.x, MongoDB, MySQL, MS Sql Server, OpenAM, Linux, Windows 7, Amazon EC2 **Tools:** JDK 1.7, Spring 3.x, SiteMesh, Groovy, Grails, Node.js, jQuery, Junit, Spock, Eclipse, Emacs, Git, GitHub, Maven, Jenkins, Vagrant, Oracle VirtualBox, Puppet, Jira

Developed new components of the IAT, the school test creation and administration tool. Created new Text To Speech implementation service using Node.js.

Object Partners, Professional Services

Senior Consultant

12/2011 - 10/2013

Menards, Web Development

Environment: JEE, Tomcat 7.x (tcServer), MySQL, Windows 7, Linux

Tools: JDK 1.6, Spring 3.1, JDBC, JSP, Velocity, jQuery, Maven, Log4j, JUnit, Mockito 1.9, Hibernate 3.6, Eclipse (Indigo), Emacs, SVN, Jenkins, Redmine, CodeCollaborator

Added new features to the Menards e-commerce web site and internal web site administration tool.

PeopleNet, Backend Services Development

Environment: JEE, Tomcat 7.x, MySQL, MS Sql Server, Linux, Windows 7, Amazon EC2

Tools: JDK 1.6, Spring 3.1, Log4j, JUnit, Mockito 1.9, RabbitMQ, 2lemetry, Eclipse (Indigo), Emacs, SVN, Maven, Jenkins, Version One

Developed new and modified existing components of the asynchronous back-end services. Created RabbitMQ AMQP based guaranteed message delivery queuing Proof-of-Concept solution, deployed to local data center and to Amazon EC2 environment. Created facade for 2lemetry m2m rest api. Created new components for the custom load test engine to perform the load testing of the new services.

Room and Board, Web Development

Environment: JEE, Tomcat 7.x, Oracle 11, Akamai, Windows 7, Linux

Tools: JDK 1.6, Spring 3.1, JDBC, JSP, SiteMesh, Freemarker 2.3, jQuery, Memcache, Ivy, Log4j, JUnit, Mockito 1.9, DbUnit 2.4, Groovy, OpenORM, Eclipse (Indigo), Emacs, SVN, Bamboo, Crucible, Jira

Developed new and modified existing components of the web site and internal web site administration tool. Focused primarily on the controller and backend services. Helped to design and implement the data versioning feature in the database schema. Created new and enhanced existing components of the UI layer using HTML, JSP, Freemarker, JavaScript and jQuery.

MoneyGram International, Systems Development

Lead Developer (Software Engineer IV)

10/2007 - 12/2011

Environment: JEE, Websphere Application Server 7.x/6.x/5.x, Tomcat 4.x/6.x, Websphere Portal 6.1, Oracle, IBM MQ, Windows XP, Linux

Tools: JDK 1.4/1.5/1.6, Spring (MVC), JSP, JSF, Portlet, Servlet, Ajax, jQuery, Wicket 1.2, Struts, JAX-WS, Axis 1.4, Ehcache 2, JDBC, XML, Ant, Log4j, JUnit, WSS4J, Castor 0.9/1.2, SoapUI, Eclipse, RAD 6/7/8, Emacs, CVS, Git, UML, Hudson, DokuWiki, Rally, XPlanner

Led the design and development of the JAX-WS based web services layer for the new Web Point of Entry system (Web POE). Created two prototypes of the new web site using JSF 2 and Spring MVC 3 frameworks. The Spring MVC based prototype became the foundation for the Web POE. Created the device authentication component using the signed java applet technology to enhance the security of the Web POE site. Demonstrated the Eclipse and Tomcat servlet container efficiency for the web development while supporting the deployment of the same code base on Websphere application server.

Lead J2EE Developer (Senior Consultant, Business Systems)

07/2004 - 10/2007

Environment: J2EE, OAS 10g Portal, Websphere 6.x/5.x, Resin 2.x, Tomcat 4.x, Apache 1.3, Oracle 10g, IBM MQ, Windows XP, Linux (RedHat), AIX

Tools: JDK 1.4, JSP, Servlet, Struts 1.1, Spring 2.0, Hibernate 3.0, JDBC, XML, XSLT, Ant 1.6, Maven, Log4j, JUnit, Eclipse, RAD, Emacs, CVS, PVCS, MKS, Together Architect, MS Visio, UML, Optimizeit Enterprise Suite (Profiler), Bugzilla

Led the design and development effort to bring aboard a number of the business partners critical for the credit card accounts acquisition business. Created new and redesigned existing web based applications in the Internet and Intranet portal environment. Created fully automated application release and deployment management process based on Ant's templated approach and CVS. Led a number of migrations of the Internet environment from the web applications side.

Compuware Corporation, Professional Services

Senior Java Developer, Full Time Consultant

07/2001 - 07/2004

HealthPartners, Center of Health Promotion

Environment: J2EE, Bea Weblogic 6.1, Tomcat 4.27, Oracle 8.1.7, MySQL 4, MS SQL Server, Windows 2000, AIX

Tools: JDK 1.3/1.4, JSP, Servlet, Struts 1.1, JDBC, XML, XSLT, JDOM, Ant, Log4j, Eclipse, Emacs, CVS, MS Visio, UML

Redesigned old web based Health Assessment application to make it more flexible, data driven. New application had been deployed under Weblogic application server and used Oracle database as the data source. Health Assessment application had been then refactored to work under HealthPartners custom portal environment.

Compuware Product Division, Software Product Development

Environment: Windows 2000, z/OS

Tools: JDK 1.4, UML, XML, JDOM, Log4j, Swing, Ant, Eclipse, Emacs, CVS, Visio

Created a TCP/IP communication driver to exchange data between Java client and Mainframe server. This driver, written in Java, was designed to be used by multiple software products for the client-server communication.

Target Corporation, E-Commerce Retail Financials

Environment: J2EE, IBM Websphere 4.02, Tomcat 3.2, Oracle 8.1.7, Solaris/NT

Tools: JDK 1.2.2/1.3, JSP, JDBC, XML, XSLT, Formula One for Java (F1J 9), Struts, Ant, WSAD, Emacs, JBuilder, Telelogic Tau UML, Visio, PVCS

Designed and developed an extendable framework for the intranet-based data retrieval and reporting system. The main goal of the framework was to provide a consistent way of presenting e-commerce financial information on the intranet in different formats such as HTML. Excel as well as graphics.

Comsys (former Cotelligent Inc.), Professional Services

Senior Software Engineer / Systems Analyst, Full Time Consultant 11/1998 - 05/2001

Innuity, Inc., E-Commerce

Environment: J2EE, Borland Inprise Application Server, Oracle 8i, Solaris/NT

Tools: JDK 1.2, EJB 1.1, JSP, JDBC, XML, UML, Rational Rose, TogetherJ, JBuilder, Emacs, SourceSafe, GNU Make, MySQL, Bugzilla, Perl

Designed and developed enterprise services for new web site builder tool. This application provided a web based user interface for the clients to make changes to their web sites.

Thomson Prometric, Education and Certification

Environment: J2EE, Bea Weblogic Application Server, Sybase 11.9.2, Solaris/NT

Tools: JDK 1.2. EJB 1.1. JSP. JConnect JDBC. Swing, UML, Rational Rose, Visio Diagram Designer. Sybase Power Designer 6.1, JBuilder, Emacs, SourceSafe, GNU Make, MySQL, Bugzilla, Perl

Designed and developed enterprise services for new Prometric Unified Financial Module. This module was the server side business logic package that provided financial services for the international corporate use by other J2EE complaint services and applications.

Medtronic, Medical Devices

Environment: Apache 1.3.6 WEB Server, Oracle 7, UNIX AIX/NT

Tools: C/PRO*C, Perl, Unix RCS

Created a number of data transfer processes in UNIX AIX 4.*, Oracle environment.

University of Minnesota Facilities Management, Education

Environment: Oracle WEB 2.1.1, Oracle 7/8, Unix AIX 4.3/NT

Tools: JDK 1.1.7, JDBC, SQL, PL/SQL, Emacs, SourceSafe

Responsible for applications software development and optimization in Unix AIX 4.3, Windows 95/NT, Oracle 7.3.3/8.0.3 environment.

Siemens, Energy Management and Information Software

Software Engineer / Systems Analyst

07/1997 - 10/1998

Environment: Oracle 7, UNIX AIX/Solaris, NT

Tools: C, C++, PRO*C, SQL, PL/SQL, Perl, RCS

Responsible for database design, development, tuning and optimization for Spectrum, an Energy Management and Information System in UNIX AIX, SUN Solaris, Windows NT, Oracle, C/C++ environment. Served as C and Oracle expert for several large-scale projects.

Center Of Financial Technologies, Financial Software

Lead Software Developer

03/1993 - 07/1997

Environment: Oracle 7, Btrieve, Windows 95, Unix Solaris/SCO

Tools: VB 4.0/5.0, VC++ 2.0, OCI, SQL, PL/SQL, Java 1.0/1.1, SourceSafe

Responsible for technical leadership in design, development and deployment of large scale financial applications for banking industry.

Education

Novosibirsk Technical University, Novosibirsk, Russia

M.S. in Computer Science and B.S. in Mathematics, 1992

Evaluated by International Education Evaluation, Inc. (March 10, 1997. REF # 116-0369)

Red Hat, Inc.

RH133 - System Administration, Red Hat Enterprise Linux 4 course, 2005

Successfully completed all Red Hat Certified Technician program requirements and is certified as a Red Hat Certified Technician, Red Hat Enterprise Linux 4.

The George Washington University School of Business

Managing IT Projects course, 2006

The George Washington University School of Business

IT Risk Management course, 2007

Object Partners

Groovy and Grails, 2012

Last modified: 2017/05/02